Guide to the Early Alumni Materials Collection MC.237
New York University Archives
Early Alumni Materials Collection
1843-1979
New York University Archives
Schenck, P. L. (Peter Lawrence), 1843-1920
Tompkins, C. M. (Charles Marshall), 1822-
Reed, Lewis B., 1824-1924
Jones, Theodore Francis, 1885-1968
Skillin, Augustus Hewlett, 1871-1932
MC.237
3.25 Linear Feet
The Early Alumni Materials Collection contains materials related to the meetings of New York University's early graduating classes. These were typically formal dinner meetings, which were first held during the class' freshman year and continued annually for the rest of the members' lives. The complete history of the collection is not known, though it is believed that the Director of the University Heights Library, Theodore F. Jones, began the collection in 1922 as part of his efforts to document the early history of NYU. The materials provide a rare glimpse into student life and alumni activities during roughly the first century of New York University's history.
Biography of Theodore F. Jones
Though the history of the Early Alumni Materials Collection is unclear, Theodore F. Jones (1885-1968) of the University Heights Library certainly had a hand in collecting some of the materials. Jones was responsible for beginning the collection that would eventually become the New York University Archives, and though documentation exists only of Jones' involvement with three folders of correspondence in the Early Alumni Materials Collection, he may have accumulated the majority of the collection. After completing a Ph.D. at Harvard University in 1910, Jones joined the faculty of New York University. He served as Director of the University Heights Library from 1923-1948 and as a professor of History from 1924-1951. His best-known work was a centennial history of NYU, New York University, 1832-1932, published by the New York University Press in 1933. Upon his retirement in 1951, Jones received an honorary Doctor of Letters degree from NYU and the status of professor emeritus. He continued to collect NYU memorabilia for the university for a short period after retiring. Biographical information about creators of individual items can be found on the item level of this collection.
Source: Theodore Jones biographical file, New York University Archives, New York University Libraries.
Custodial History
The Early Alumni Materials Collection likely did not have a single creator or even a singular purpose for its creation. Rather, it seems to have accumulated gradually under a succession of custodians who both actively solicited and happened to be given materials and ephemera related to the annual meetings of nineteenth and early twentieth century graduating classes of New York University. The earliest materials in the collection date from 1843, and the most recent date from 1987 (though they refer to the Class of 1937).
Theodore F. Jones, library director at the University Heights campus in the early 20th century, began accumulating materials for a "New York University Collection" in 1922. This collection was meant both to provide the library with documentation of the early history of NYU, and to support Jones' work on a centennial history of the university (New York University, 1832-1932, published by the New York University Press in 1933). Only the correspondence in Folders 1-3 of Box 1 can be definitively attributed to Jones, however, and some later materials in the collection are attributed to other custodians.
According to correspondence found in the collection's administrative file, items relating to the Class of 1894 were donated to NYU by the Estate of John V. Irwin in 1979. These items were discovered at 64 West 3rd Street and transferred to to the University Archives in 1994.
The collection was present in more or less its current form in the University Archives as early as 1983, when it was titled the "Class Collection" and partially processed. However, other information about its provenance has been lost. It seems to have been through multiple cycles of accumulation and dispersal throughout its lifetime. Pieces of correspondence within the collection refer to materials that are no longer included in it, and some ephemera included in the collection when it was processed in 2013 were not included in the 1983 inventory. However, while the collection is somewhat of a fractured whole, the materials within it are still quite illuminating sources of information about the organization and activities of early graduating classes of NYU.
Source: Theodore F. Jones, The New York University Collection (New York: New York University, 1938).
Scope and Content
The bulk of the collection relates to the meetings of NYU's early graduating classes. These were typically formal dinner meetings, which began in the members' freshman years and continued annually until all but one member of the class had passed away. The Class of 1843 Minute Book documents this fact particularly well: it includes the complete minutes of each meeting from 1843 until 1914, when Lewis B. Reed noted that he had become the sole surviving member of the class. The Class of 1894 minute books are similarly detailed. Portions of minutes from other classes' meetings are also included in Series III of the collection.
Series I includes scattered correspondence among members of various graduating classes, as well as between University Heights Library Director Theodore F. Jones and alumni who owned photographs of their graduating classes. Jones wished to add the photographs to the NYU library's collections. It is not known whether these photographs were ever a part of the Early Alumni Materials Collection, though they are not included in the 1983 inventory.
Series II includes menus from class dinners that were held at restaurants and clubs throughout the city between 1854 and 1977. They provide a small cross-section of the evolution of New York City food culture over one and a quarter centuries. Series IV includes a handful of publications created by and about members of graduating classes.
Biographical information about individual alumni from various classes comprises a large component of the collection. The class catalogs, directories, and record books in Series V list alumni names, addresses, occupations, and other identifying characteristics, including achievements pre- and post-graduation. The scrapbooks in Series VI include more detailed biographical information about alumni, particularly when they were created by a single alumnus, as in the Memories of P.L. Schenck scrapbook and the Augustus Hewlett Skillen scrapbook. Other scrapbooks document class activities as a whole, as in the Class of 1890 scrapbooks, or consist simply of the signatures of the members of the graduating class, as in the three autograph books dating from 1843-1853. Biographical information about individual alumni can also be found among the memorabilia in Series VII, along with information about student life at NYU in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Some materials in the collection are in poor condition due to their age. Where possible, copies of the materials have been created to enable researchers to access the information within them. Certain scrapbooks have been transferred to the Barbara Goldsmith Conservation and Preservation Department for treatment and are not accessible to researchers until they have been treated.
Arrangement
The Early Alumni Materials Collection is arranged into series according to the genre of the materials. Within each series, the materials are organized chronologically by the date of the graduating class that produced them. This method of chronological organization was retained from the partial processing of the collection that occurred in 1983. However, series have been imposed in order to create a more manageable order in a collection that is otherwise piecemeal. This collection is arranged into 7 series.
The Early Alumni Materials Collection is arranged into series according to the genre of the materials. Within each series, the materials are organized chronologically by the date of the graduating class that produced them. This method of chronological organization was retained from the partial processing of the collection that occurred in 1983. The materials have subsequently been arranged in 7 series to reflect the different formats present in the collection.
Series I: Correspondence
Correspondence
Events
Minutes
Publications
Class catalogs and directories
Scrapbooks and memory books
Memorabilia
Related Materials
See the Alumni Scrapbook and Alumni Association Minutes and the Records of the Alumni Federation of New York University, Inc., for more information about New York University alumni associations and activities.
The University Archives Photograph Collection contains the class photographs described in the Theodore F. Jones correspondence in Series I.
Conditions Governing Access
Repository permission is required for access. Please contact New York University Archives, (212) 998-2641, university-archives@nyu.edu.
Menus.; Class reunions; Scrapbooks.; Minutes (administrative records); Directories.; University of the City of New York; New York University; New York University -- Students -- 20th century; New York University -- Students -- 19th century; Bill, Charles Alfred, 1871-
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Theodore F. Jones' correspondence with Class of 1863-Class of 1879 alumni, 1930-1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Theodore F. Jones' correspondence with Class of 1880-Class of 1888 alumni, 1930-1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Theodore F. Jones' correspondence with Class of 1889-Class of 1892 alumni, 1930-1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence of and about the Class of 1843, 1909-1914 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Class of 1863 correspondence, 1866, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Class of 1890 correspondence, 1925-1936 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Class of 1894 correspondence, 1906-1954 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Class of 1914 correspondence, 1951-1963 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series II: Events
  - Class of 1843 Annual Reunion dinner menus, 1862-1914 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Class of 1844: Reminiscences of C.M. Tompkins (speech given at Alumni Association meeting), 1894; Tompkins, C. M. (Charles Marshall), 1822- (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Biography of C.M. Tompkins
    Charles Marshall (C.M.) Tompkins was born in Somers, New York, on August 13, 1822. He earned a Bachelor of Arts degree from the University of the City of New York in 1843, where he was Vice President of the Eucleian Society. From 1850 to 1854, he served as a lawyer, judge, and postmaster in Fond Du Lac, Wisconsin. He then became principal examiner at the Pension Office in Washington, D.C. Source: General Alumni Society of New York University, New York University Alumni Catalogue, 1833-1907 (Boston: Colonial Press, 1906), 22.
  - Class of 1845 third triennial meeting and dinner announcement, 1854 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Class of 1851 Reunion dinner menu, 1871 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Class of 1875: 1915 reunion program and 1875 Graduating Address of Isaac Franklin Russell (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Class of 1883 Annual Dinner menus, 1882-1908 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Class of 1890 Class Day and Commencement materials (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Class of 1890 35th Reunion materials, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Class of 1890 42nd Reunion materials, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Class of 1897 Annual Banquet materials, 1894-1937 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Class of 1904 Third Annual Dinner menu and program, 1903 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Class of 1907 Annual Dinner menus, 1906-1908 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Class of 1908 Annual Dinner menus and programs, 1908-1912 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Class of 1909 event programs, clippings, 1908-1912 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Class of 1912 School of Law banquet menu (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - School of Commerce Tenth Annual Dinner menu and program, Classes of 1912-1914 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Class of 1914 School of Law banquet menu and program (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Class of 1914 event programs, 1910-1915 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Class of 1915 Annual Dinner menu, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Class of 1915 School of Law Senior Banquet menu and program (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Class of 1917 Freshman dinner menu, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Class of 1917 School of Law annual banquet menu, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Class of 1918 School of Law Annual Banquet menu, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Class of 1922 Annual Reunion menus and programs, 1952-1977 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Class of 1924 Sophomore Smoker and Banquet menu and program, 1922 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Class of 1929 50th Reunion invitation, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Class of 1937 50th anniversary of graduation program, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - School of Medicine 125th Anniversary dinner materials, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Series III: Minutes
  - Class of 1843 Minute Book, 1843-1914 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Class of 1862 Minute Book, ca. 1858 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Class of 1879 Constitution and Minute Book, 1876-1879 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Class of 1894 Minute Book, 1893-1919 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Class of 1894 Minute Book, 1920-1959 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Access Restrictions
    The paper in this scrapbook is in poor condition. Researchers should consult photocopies of the original located in Box 4, Folder 1.
  - Class of 1894 Minute Book photocopy, 1920-1959 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Class of 1912: Minutes of the 60th Annual Reunion, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Series IV: Publications
  - "A Student at New York University in 1847: Excerpts from the Diary of John E. Parsons", 1954 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - "Twenty-Five Years Ago", 1885 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - "Ernest Howard Crosby: A Forgotten Tolstoyan Anti-Militarist and Anti-Imperialist" by Perry E. Gianakos, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Twenty Bohemian Folk-Songs, translated and compiled by Rev. Vincent Pisek, D.D., 1894 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - "My Hero" by Crosby Field Frank and "NYU Pen Topography" by F.M. Arnolt, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Series V: Class catalogs, directories, and record books
  - Catalogue of the Professors and Students of the Junior Class, 1853-1854 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Class of 1890 directory, 1905 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Class of 1890 directory, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Class of 1890 directory, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Class of 1890 directory, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Class of 1890 directory, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Class of 1894 25th Anniversary record, 1922 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Class of 1896 Medical College class book, 1896-1916 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Class of 1899 Law School 25th Anniversary directory, 1924 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Class of 1900 record book, 1900-1910 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Class of 1901 directory, circa 1900 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Class of 1902 record, circa 1912 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Class of 1905 15th Anniversary record, 1920 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Class of 1906 roster, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Class of 1914 "25 Year Violet", 1939 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Class of 1915 "Tattler", 1920 (Box 5, Folder 9)